{"tossups": [{"question": "Description acceptable. The name of this policy originated from a translation of a posthumously-published history by Engelbert Kaempfer (KAYMP-fur). The professor Erik Laxman sent his son Adam on a diplomatic mission to return several lost nationals to the area a fected by this policy. Under this policy, subjects received a reward of 500 pieces of silver for discovering a bateren (bah-tay-ren), and a reward of 300 pieces of silver for discovering an iruman (ee-roo-mahn). The establishment of this policy was preceded by a skirmish in which Nicolaes Couckebacker (koo-keh-bah-ker) bombarded rebels stationed in Hara Castle. This policy increased the regional power of the Matsumae (mah-tsoo-mah-eh) and So clans. In an exception to this policy, several scienti c texts were brought in from the island of Dejima, beginning the trend of \"Dutch learning.\" This policy was ended by the Convention of Kanagawa, which resulted from the gunboat diplomacy of Matthew Perry. For 10 points, identify this policy of the Tokugawa Shogunate that prevented residents from leaving, and foreigners from entering, Japan.", "answer": "sakoku [or Japanese isolationism; accept any answers mentioning the ban of foreigners, Christians, Europeans, etc. from Japan; accept Nihon or Tokugawa Shogunate in place of \"Japan\"; do not accept the similar-sounding, but completely wrong, \"sengoku\"]", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In fiber optic communication systems, noisy variation in this quantity occurs due to the Gordon-Mollenauer (moh-len-\"ow\"-er) effect. Bohm and Pines developed an approximation named for this quantity in which single-particle degrees of freedom interact via a short-range screened Coulomb force, leading to the Lindhard formula for the permittivity of an electron gas. One form of this quantity includes a factor of \u201cone plus n plus m\u201d for the T\u00b7E\u00b7M-sub-n-m mode of a Gaussian beam and is named for Gouy (\"gooey\"). Another form of this quantity belongs to the holonomy group of a Hermitian line bundle and arises when at least two Hamiltonian parameters of a system undergo adiabatic transport along a closed loop, as shown by Michael Berry. The quotient of angular frequency and wavenumber is this quantity\u2019s namesake velocity. For 10 points, name this quantity that may di fer for two light waves by up to 360 degrees.", "answer": "phase shift [accept Gordon-Mollenauer phase noise or random phase approximation or Gouy phase or geometric phase or Pancharatnam-Berry phase or phase velocity]", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "An error-correction scheme that relies on values constructed by using non-singular projective curves defined over one of these constructs is the Goppa code. These structures are often represented using the Conway polynomial, and they are used to recursively factor polynomials in Berlekamp's algorithm. The Diffie-Hellman algorithm relies on the infeasibility of finding f to the x y, where f is a generator of the multiplicative group over one of these structures. These \"perfect\" structures have a Frobenius endomorphism that is an automorphism. Wedderburn's little theorem states that every division ring is one of these structures, a simple example of which are the residue classes modulo p. An order equal to the power of a prime characterizes, for 10 points, what algebraic structures that are closed under two operations and have a whole number of elements?", "answer": "finite fields [prompt on fields]", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This text's \"ethnographic imagination\" is the subject of a book by Carol Dougherty that argues that the description of the creation of an object in this text is a metaphor for the creation of the text itself. This text's repetitive use of comparative language that inverts traditional social and sexual roles is dubbed \"reverse simile\" in an essay by Helene Foley. Peter von der Mu\u0308hll (MUUL) theorized that a redactor 'B' combined works by authors 'A' and 'T' to produce this text, which Henry Fielding called \"the eating-est epic.\" Samuel Butler argued that a woman from Sicily authored this text and inserted herself into the story as a princess who encounters a shipwrecked man while washing clothes on the island of Scheria. This text chronologically follows a lost epic called the Nostoi, or \"returns.\" For 10 points, name this ancient Greek poem whose female characters include Nausicaa (naw-SIK-ay-ah) and Penelope.", "answer": "The Odyssey [or Odysseia] [Editor's note: The object referred to in the first sentence is the raft Odysseus builds on Calypso's island.]", "subcategory": "Literature Classical", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The street grid of a campus in this state is o fset from the grid of the surrounding city by 12.25 degrees, inspiring the design of a building which alternates between following the two grids. A museum in this state was the center of a 1990 obscenity trial when it displayed a Robert Mapplethorpe exhibition; that museum moved in 2003 to Zaha Hadid's  rst American building. This state is home to the Longaberger Company headquarters, which is shaped like a giant basket. The Wexner Center for the Arts, designed by Peter Eisenman, is in this state. Colorful cars are suspended from the ceiling in the atrium of a museum in this state, which includes a tetrahedral glass tent descending from a white tower which rises from the water of a nearby lake. For 10 points, name this state home to I.M. Pei's Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.", "answer": "Ohio", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Other", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A miniature portrait of one of these people washing sausages was rediscovered in 2011. The Royal Yacht HMY Fubbs got its name from a nickname for one of these people. One of these people had Nonsuch Palace torn down and sold the parts to pay o f gambling debts, and was targeted by a satirical \"petition\" issued a ter the Bawdy House Riots. Rumors that one of these people had secretly gotten married were circulated during the Exclusion Crisis. One of these people notoriously started out as an orange-seller. On his deathbed, a man asked his brother to \"let not [one of these people] starve.\" Lucy Walter and Barbara Palmer were two of these people, whose existence annoyed Catherine of Braganza. For 10 points, name these people, including Nell Gwyn, who had a fairs with the king who took power in the Restoration.", "answer": "mistresses of Charles II of England [accept synonyms for \"mistresses\"; prompt on actresses until \"Fubbs\" is read; prompt on partial answer]", "subcategory": "History British", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This  eld's \"Social Transformation\" was chronicled by American Prospect co-founder Paul Starr in a book about the loss of its professional sovereignty. In The Social System, Talcott Parsons controversially argued that this  eld was a form of policing for conditionally \"sanctioned deviance.\" It's not education, but its \"nemesis\" was extensively critiqued by Ivan Illich, who argued that this  eld o ten creates more problems than it solves. A work of anthropology on this  eld describes Neil Ernst and Peggy Philp, who fail to grasp the shamanistic culture of immigrants in Merced, California. The Spirit Catches You and You Fall Down is a classic in the anthropology of this  eld, whose late 18th-century epistemological break originated its namesake \"gaze\" according to a work by Michel Foucault. For 10 points, name this  eld of study whose medieval \"Canon\" was authored by Avicenna, and whose classical pioneers include Hippocrates and Galen.", "answer": "medicine [or synonyms like medical science]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This playwright was translated and  rst introduced to the U.S. by an actor who later became a Hollywood star playing Dr. Fu Manchu and Charlie Chan. In one of his plays, the scene abruptly changes from a lawyer's o  ce to a commencement ceremony, in which dancers refuse to crown the lawyer with a laurel wreath. Near the end of that play by this man, the deans of four university faculties argue about whether or not a door should be opened. One of this playwright's protagonists frequently talks about \"all the right-thinking\" people. The locations of Foulstrand and Fairhaven are contrasted in a play of his that ends with a castle burning and the  lower bud on its roof bursting into a giant chrysanthemum. Thisplaywright wrote about Indra's daughter descending to Earth in A Dream Play. For 10 points, name this native of Sweden who created Miss Julie.", "answer": "August Strindberg", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "An enlarged blood vessel compressing this structure can be displaced in the Jannetta procedure. A condition a fecting this structure can be treated by injecting glycerol into Meckel's cave. HSV-1 usually lies latent in the ganglia of this nerve. Examples of this structure's namesake auto\u00c2\u00b7nomic ceph\u00c2\u00b7al\u00c2\u00b7gias include cluster headaches. The \"suicide disease\" is a nickname for this structure's extremely painful neuralgia. Its nucleus receives touch-position and pain-temperature input. Whereas the oph\u00c2\u00b7thal\u00c2\u00b7mic and maxillary branches of this nerve are purely sensory, its mandibular branch innervates the muscles of biting and chewing. For 10 points, identify this fifth and largest cranial nerve, named for the fact that it has three major branches.", "answer": "trigeminal nerve [or the fifth cranial nerve before it is mentioned; accept CN V before \"  th\" is read]", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Fritz Kreisler convinced his own concert manager to arrange this musician's wildly successful debut 1928 American tour. This musician frequently performed a transcription of the Christmas song \"El Noi de la Mare\" (el NOY deh lah MAH-ruh) as an encore piece. Heitor Villa-Lobos (ai-TOR vee-yuh-LOW-bowsh) transformed street music from this man's country into a set of twelve etudes dedicated to this musician, who also commissioned the Fantasia for a Gentleman. This musician and his teacher, Miguel Llobet (yoh-BET), worked together to make Isaac Albeniz's music a key part of their instrument's repertoire. Breaking from tradition established by Fernando Sor and Francisco Tarrega, this musician played using a combination of both  ngernails and  ngertips, and he endorsed the use of nylon rather than catgut strings. For 10 points, name this Spanish musician, the father of classical guitar.", "answer": "Andre\u0301s Segovia [or Andre\u0301s Segovia Torres, 1st Marquis of Salobren\u0303a]", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A character speculates that poor and downtrodden citizens were speci cally relocated to the \"City Paranoiac\" to experience these events. A somber re lection on parents \"leaving their children alone in the forest\" is occasioned by one of these events that interrupts a pantomime of Hansel and Gretel. A hymn from the protagonist's distant ancestor William is o fered just before last of these events occurs, interrupting the closing words: \"Now everybody\u00c2\u2014\" The young sex slave Gottfried sacri ces himself by climbing into a device with the serial number 00000 (\"zero-zero-zero-zero-zero\") used for one of these events. Roger Mexico determines that the same Poisson distribution is followed by these events and an American lieutenant's sexual encounters around London. For 10 points, name these destructive attacks seemingly predicted by Tyrone Slothrop in Gravity's Rainbow.", "answer": "V-2 rocket strikes in Gravity's Rainbow [or V-2 rocket attacks; or V-2 strikes; or obvious equivalents]", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A diplomatic attempt to perform this action was bungled by Romulus Saunders, who spoke \"no language but English, and even this...sometimes murder[ed].\" This action was justified by analogy to \"tearing down [a] burning house\" as the only way to prevent flames from consuming one's home. This action was described as a \"law of political gravity\" such as affects a ripe fruit by John Quincy Adams. This goal of the \"Young America\" movement was attempted in an e fort that Robert E. Lee and Jefferson Davis refused to lead, which was bankrolled by Mississippi governor John Quitman. This action, which would secure the center of George Bickley's \"Golden Circle,\" was attempted in two failed expeditions by Narciso Lopez. Pierre Soule\u0301 (SOOL), James Buchanan, and John Mason justified this action as a defense of slavery in the Ostend Manifesto. For 10 points, name this longtime goal of antebellum Democratic expansionists, which would have added to the Union an island south of Florida.", "answer": "annexing Cuba [or conquering Cuba; or buying Cuba; or making Cuba part of the United States or other equivalents; or Cuban statehood]", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A member of this profession is suspected of stealing a queen's jewels until the queen realizes his jewels are actually of higher quality than hers, a ter which he is set free and married o f to the princess. That member of this profession visits a society whose members walk around naked, but gets kicked out because of his incredulity at the fact that they celebrate at funerals instead of mourning. Following the directions given by a character of this profession, a sultan  nds a man who is half human and half stone. That member of this profession tells the story of \"The Wazir and the Sage Duban\" to a character whom he meets a ter  nding a copper jar with the seal of Solomon on its cap. When o fered the choice of his manner of death, a member of this profession tricks the being who made the o fer into returning to his bottle. For 10 points, name this profession of a character who encounters a jinni in the second story from the Arabian Nights.", "answer": "3sherman [or angler; or piscator]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A pragmatist interpretation of this text was illustrated through the example of a judge who applies precedents to decide on tort law in A Spirit of Trust, an analytic re-con guring of this text by Robert Brandom. An attack on physiognomy ( z-ee-ON-oh-mee) and phrenology in this text quotes Lichtenberg that a man in the physiognomist's grasp could make himself \"incomprehensible\" again through a \"box on the ear.\" This text de nes the \"Unhappy Consciousness\" as an outgrowth of skepticism which must  nd relief in submission to a priest. A more famous passage in this text describes how forced labor and fear causes a  gure to destroy the \"alien negative\" and make itself a \"negative...on its own account,\" while his counterpart enjoys only \"unessential consciousness.\" That passage describes the relationship between \"lordship and bondsman.\" For 10 points, name this philosophical text tracing the progression of thought to \"absolute knowledge\" through the process of dialectic, the most famous work of G.W.F. Hegel.", "answer": "The Phenomenology of Spirit [or Pha\u0308nomenologie des Geistes]", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "During this event, a group of women tore the clothes o f a singer known for going around wearing a men's riding habit and organizing battalions of armed women. During this event, an author wrote the play The Black Market to protest slavery, but the text was burned a ter her death. A society mobilizing working-class women was founded during this event by an actress who kept  ghting a ter being shot through the arm. A Dutch woman named Etta Palm d'Aelders (d'-\"ALE\"-ders) organized like-minded \"Female Friends of Truth\" during this event. During this general time period, the \"marvelous ones\" popularized Greek-style dresses within a youth subculture that included the \"incredibles.\" Early in this time period, thousands of pitchfork-wielding women incensed by the high price of bread dragged cannons to a palace, forcing the royal family to return to the capital city. For 10 points, name this historical event during which women marched on Versailles, and Charlotte Corday assassinated the agitator Jean-Paul Marat.", "answer": "the French Revolution [prompt on answers such as the Directory, the Reign of Terror, the Thermidorian Reaction, etc.]", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This novel's protagonist repeats to himself William Camden's rhyme \"Betwixt the stirrup and the ground, mercy I asked, mercy I found.\" When its protagonist visits his lawyer Prewitt, Prewitt quotes a line from Doctor Faustus about how \"this is Hell, nor are we out of it.\" The title of this novel is used as a metaphor for human nature when a character says that it won't change even if you \"bite it all the way down.\" This novel describes a variant of the newspaper competition \"Lobby Lud,\" in which readers have to spot a person named \"Kolley Kibber.\" This novel's villain marries Rose, and its protagonist, Ida Arnold, tries to save Rose from him and get justice for Fred Hale. This novel's villain is the teenage gang leader Pinkie Brown. For 10 points, name this Graham Greene novel set in a seaside resort town in England.", "answer": "Brighton Rock", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Restoration e forts at this location were led by Henry Buckland, who named his daughter a ter it. A park named a ter this location is home to the  rst set of full-scale sculptures of dinosaurs. A disaster at this location destroyed much of the work of television pioneer John Logie Baird, who set up his laboratory here. A rally held at this European location convinced Robert Baden-Powell to form the Girl Guides as a counterpart to the Boy Scouts. This location was given its name by Douglas Jerrold, who used the pseudonym Amelia Mouser for Punch magazine, and it was relocated to Sydenham Hill a ter serving its most famous purpose. Its architect reused his rainproof \"ridge-and-furrow\" roof design from his greenhouse in Chatsworth. That architect, who worked with Charles Fox on this structure, is Joseph Paxton. For 10 points, name this building that incorporated 900,000 square feet of glass and served as the centerpiece for London's Great Exhibition of 1851.", "answer": "Crystal Palace", "subcategory": "History British", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One of these animals appears to be looking up the dress of a passed-out woman in the painting The Drunken Couple. Four heads of these animals in di ferent poses make up a study by Frans Snyders, who o ten included them as the only living animals amongst his scenes of dead animals. A boy holds an eel in his le t hand and one of these animals in his right hand in a painting by Judith Leyster. These animals appear in both of the Jan Steen paintings which inspired two of Miro\u0301's three Dutch Interiors. One of these animals walks over some oysters on the le t of Chardin's The Ray. Paintings by Jan Steen depict families teaching these animals to read and to dance. For 10 points, name these domestic animals o ten depicted  ghting with dogs in Dutch art.", "answer": "cats [accept synonyms like kitties or kittens]", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A practitioner of this religion named Richard Baker resigned a ter it was revealed that he was having an a fair with the wife of one of his followers, in one of a rash of sex scandals this religion faced in the 1980s. This religious tradition was popularized in Germany by a Nazi psychotherapist who developed \"initiation therapy,\" Karlfried Graf Du\u0308rckheim. Philip Kapleau founded a center for the study of this tradition in Rochester, New York and wrote a book about its \"three pillars.\" This tradition was largely popularized in the west by D. T. Suzuki, who drew parallels between it and the thought of Meister Eckhart. Books about the \"way\" and the \"spirit\" of this tradition were written by Alan Watts. For 10 points, name this branch of Mahayana Buddhism whose practitioners ponder koans.", "answer": " Zen Buddhism [or Chan Buddhism; prompt on Buddhism; prompt on Mahayana Buddhism]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "It's not the aldol reaction, but the fact that this reaction proceeds through a chair-like transition state was elucidated in the Doering-Roth (\"during-roth\") experiment. A common route for synthesizing acyl pyr\u00c2\u00b7rol\u00c2\u00b7idines couples the aza-variant of this reaction with a Mannich (\"manic\") reaction. Delta-epsilon unsaturated carbonyls are generated a ter a keto-enol taut\u00c2\u00b7o\u00c2\u00b7mer\u00c2\u00b7iz\u00c2\u00b7ation in the oxy-variant of this reaction. A single peak is observed on an H-NMR spectrum of bullvalene (\"bull\"-VAY-leen) because of  luxionality ( luk-shon-AL-ity) due to degenerate occurrences of this reaction. The namesake of this reaction also developed a reaction to convert N-oxides of tertiary amines to an alkene using mCPBA (\"m-C-P-B-A\") through his namesake elimination. This pericyclic reaction involves the heat-catalyzed isomerization of one- ve-di\u00c2\u00b7enes. For 10 points, name this reaction, which like the Claisen rearrangement exempli es a three- ve sigmatropic reaction.", "answer": "Cope rearrangement [do not accept \"Cope elimination\"]", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Emmeline Pankhurst's daughter Sylvia was invited to live in this city in 1956 a ter supporting an anticolonial movement in the 1930s and 1940s. In 1894, this city's founder ordered thousands of eucalyptus trees to be imported from Australia, some of which still stand on its Mount Entoto. Its landmarks include the Tiglachin Monument, which bears depictions of Cuban soldiers, and one that commemorates the victims of a massacre at the Debre Libanos monastery. This city's name, which means \"new  lower,\" was coined by the empress Taytu Betul. It is one of its country's two \"chartered\" cities, along with Dire Dawa (dee-ray dah-wah), and is the headquarters of the African Union. A rezoning plan that would expand this city's borders is the subject of protests by the oppressed majority Oromo ethnic group. For 10 points, name this city founded by Menelik II, which was the seat of power for Haile Selassie.", "answer": "Addis Ababa", "category": "Geography"}], "bonuses": []}